Right, everyone, let’s make a start.
Over the past few sessions, we’ve been considering the reasons why some world languages
are in decline,
and today I’m going to introduce another factor that affects languages,
and the speakers of those languages,
and that’s technology and, in particular, digital technology.
In order to illustrate its effect, I’m going to focus on the Icelandic
language,
which is spoken by around 321,000 people, most of whom live in Iceland –
an island in the North Atlantic Ocean.
The problem for this language is not the number of speakers – even though
this number is small.
Nor is it about losing words to other languages, such as English.
In fact, the vocabulary of Icelandic is continually increasing because when speakers need a
new word for something, they tend to create one, rather than borrowing from another
language.
All this makes Icelandic quite a special language – it’s changed very little in
the past millennium, yet it can handle twenty-first-century concepts related to the use of computers
and digital technology.
Take, for example, the word for web browser … this is vafri in Icelandic,
which comes from the verb ‘to wander’.
I can’t think of a more appropriate term because that’s exactly what you do
mentally when you browse the internet.
Then there’s an Icelandic word for podcast – which is too hard to pronounce!
And so on.
Icelandic, then, is alive and growing,
but – and it’s a big but – young Icelanders spend a great deal
of time in the digital world and this world is predominantly English.
Think about smartphones.
They didn’t even exist until comparatively recently,
but today young people use them all the time to read books, watch TV
or films, play games, listen to music,
and so on.
Obviously, this is a good thing in many respects because it promotes their bilingual
skills,
but the extent of the influence of English in the virtual world is staggering
and it’s all happening really fast.
For their parents and grandparents, the change is less concerning
because they already have their native-speaker skills in Icelandic.
But for young speakers – well, the outcome is a little troubling.
For example, teachers have found that playground conversations in Icelandic secondary schools can be
conducted entirely in English,
while teachers of much younger children have reported situations where their classes find it
easier to say what is in a picture using English, rather than Icelandic.
The very real and worrying consequence of all this is that the young generation
in Iceland is at risk of losing its mother tongue.
Of course, this is happening to other European languages too,
but while internet companies might be willing to offer, say, French options in their
systems, it’s much harder for them to justify the expense of doing the same
for a language that has a population the size of a French town, such
as Nice.
The other drawback of Icelandic is the grammar,
which is significantly more complex than in most languages.
At the moment, the tech giants are simply not interested in tackling this.
So, what is the Icelandic government doing about this?
Well, large sums of money are being allocated to a language technology fund that
it is hoped will lead to the development of Icelandic sourced apps
and other social media and digital systems,
but clearly this is going to be an uphill struggle.
On the positive side, they know that Icelandic is still the official language of education
and government.
It has survived for well over a thousand years and the experts predict that
its future in this nation state is sound and will continue to be so.
However, there’s no doubt that it’s becoming an inevitable second choice in young people’s
lives.
This raises important questions.
When you consider how much of the past is tied up in a language,
will young Icelanders lose their sense of their own identity?
Another issue that concerns the government of Iceland is this.
If children are learning two languages through different routes, neither of which they are
fully fluent in, will they be able to express themselves properly?